<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-automation" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Automation</title>
<indexterm><primary>automation</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Automation is the means by which many controls in Ardour (faders,
plugin controls, mute and solo, and so on) can be &lsquo;automated&rsquo;, so that
their values change over time.  This is commonly used to assist with
mixing a track; vocal levels may be brought up and down as required,
for example.  This chapter describes the ways in which automation may
be set up and edited.
</para>

<section>
<title>Adding an automation lane</title>

By default, a track has no automation.  To add some, the first step is
to open an automation &lsquo;lane&rsquo; for the track.  This looks much like an
additional track, but can be considered a &lsquo;child&rsquo; of its parent track.

<para>
To create an automation lane for an audio track, click the &lsquo;a&rsquo; button
in the track controls area.  A menu will open which contains a list of
the things which can be automated for the track.  By default, this
will just be &lsquo;fader&rsquo; and &lsquo;pan&rsquo;, but if the track has any plugins,
their controls will also be listed in this menu.
</para>

<para>
Choosing, for example, &lsquo;fader&rsquo; opens a new automation lane, as shown
in <xref linkend="fig-automation-lane"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-automation-lane"> 
  <title>An automation lane</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/automation-lane&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
We now have an automation lane for the track &lsquo;up_with_people.stereo&rsquo;
which controls its fader level.  The automation lane's controls area
includes the name of the parameter being automated, a handy fader for
adjusting the level of the parameter, a button to select the
automation mode, and a &lsquo;cross&rsquo; button to hide the automation lane.
Hiding the automation lane merely removes it from sight; it does not
have any effect on the automation that the lane contains.
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Automation modes</title>

<para>
Clicking on the automation lane's mode button (which initially says &lsquo;Manual&rsquo;) offers four options:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem> <emphasis>Manual</emphasis> &mdash; in this mode the automation will be ignored on playback.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>Play</emphasis> &mdash; in this mode the automation will be &lsquo;played
  back'; in other words, when the session is playing back, the track's
  controls will be manipulated by any automation that has been set up.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>Write</emphasis> &mdash; when the session is being played back, any
  automation lanes in &lsquo;write&rsquo; mode will store data from the current
  value of their parameter at each instant.  In other words, one way
  to create automation data is to set &lsquo;write&rsquo; mode, play the session
  back, then adjust the parameter (in this case the fader) of the
  track as required.  Your movements will be recorded and written as
  automation.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>Touch &mdash; <!-- doesn't seem to work right now --></emphasis>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>
<section><title>Creating automation</title>

<para>
There are two basic ways to create automation data.  Firstly, one may
use the &lsquo;write&rsquo; mode, as discussed in the previous section.  To see
this in action for our example fader lane, simply select &lsquo;write&rsquo;,
start the session, and move the track's fader around a bit.  When you
stop the transport, an automation line will appear on the lane to show
you the moves that you made on the fader.
</para>

<para>
The other option is to draw the automation with the mouse.  Clicking
in an automation lane with in &lsquo;select/move objects&rsquo; mode
(<imagedata scale="75" fileref="screenshots/tool-objects&scs;"/>) will create a new automation point.
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Editing automation</title>

<para>
Automation may be edited using the mouse in the automation lane.
Hovering the mouse over an automation line will put red squares at
each node of the line; these can be dragged around to move them.
</para>

<para>
You can also &modone;-right-click to display a dialogue box to change
the precise value of an automation point, or
&modtertiary;-right-click to delete a point.
</para>

<para>
Multiple points can be selected so that they can be moved as a group;
either &modone;-left-click to select additional points, or drag a
&lsquo;lassoo&rsquo; rectangle over a group of points to select several at once.
</para>

<para>
Finally, points may be cut, copied and pasted, just as regions, by
selecting them and using the standard key shortcuts <keycap>&modone;-X</keycap>
for cut, <keycap>&modone;-C</keycap> for copy or
<keycap>&modone;-V</keycap> for paste).  Pastes are made at the edit
point.
</para>

</section>
<section><title>MIDI &lsquo;automation&rsquo;</title>

As discussed in <xref linkend="sec-midi-non-note"/>, a variety of MIDI
message types are presented in Ardour as automation.  Lanes for these
messages can be opened, just as with audio tracks, by clicking on the
&lsquo;a&rsquo; button in a MIDI track's control area and selecting a parameter.
The menu is much more extensive for MIDI, since there is an option for
each parameter on each MIDI channel.

Note that because of the way MIDI automation is stored (with the
region), it is not possible to draw MIDI automation in an area of the
lane where its parent track does not have a region.  If you want to
add automation without any note data, simply create an empty region
before adding the automation.

</section>
</chapter>
