<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-control" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Control surfaces</title>

<para>
Whilst Ardour can be controlled using the keyboard and mouse, a
<emphasis>control surface</emphasis> can make life a lot easier.  This
is some external piece of hardware that has some combination of
buttons, knobs, faders and displays that you can use to control
Ardour, mimicing to some extent the feel of having a real mixing desk
or tape machine.
</para>

<para>
Ardour directly supports several different control surfaces, and some
of those that are not ready-to-use can be set up if you are willing to
spend some extra time configuring things.
</para>

<para>
The support for control surfaces is divided up into groups based on
the protocol that the surface uses to communicate.  The next two
sections discuss these two groups.
</para>

<section><title>Generic MIDI surfaces</title>

<para>
&lsquo;Generic MIDI surfaces&rsquo; are those that have a fairly
simple protocol based on MIDI.  This covers quite a wide range of
surfaces.  A specific surface requires Ardour to have a
<emphasis>binding map</emphasis>, which describes the MIDI messages
that the surface sends when its controls are operated, and any
messages it expects to receive in return.
</para>

<para>
Ardour's generic MIDI surface code has support for the following devices:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Behringer DDX3216</listitem>
<listitem>Behringer BCF2000</listitem>
<listitem>EMU XBoard 61</listitem>
<listitem>Korg nanoKONTROL</listitem>
<listitem>M-Audio Axiom 25 (its transport controls)</listitem>
<listitem>M-Audio Oxygen8 V2</listitem>
<listitem>Roland SI-24</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
To set up a generic MIDI control, it is first necessary to connect it
to your computer.  This may be done with MIDI or USB.  Those devices
which use USB generally appear as MIDI ports to Ardour.
</para>

<para>
The next step is to enable the generic MIDI surface in Ardour and
select the map that Ardour should use, based on the hardware that you
have.  Open the <guilabel>Ardour Preferences</guilabel> dialogue and
select the <guilabel>User interaction</guilabel> tab.  At the bottom
of the window is a list of the available control surface groups.  Tick
the <guilabel>Enabled</guilabel> box for &lsquo;Generic MIDI&rsquo;.
If your device has motorised faders, or knobs or displays that
indicate their status, Ardour can provide feedback so that the
surface's state matches that of Ardour's mixer.  To enable this, tick
the <guilabel>Feedback</guilabel> checkbox.
</para>

<para>
Next, double-click the &lsquo;Generic MIDI&rsquo; entry in the
dialogue box, and a settings window will appear.  Choose the device
that you are using from the drop-down list.
</para>

<para>
Finally, you need to connect the MIDI ports of your device to Ardour.
Open the MIDI connections manager and connect Ardour's &lsquo;MIDI
control out&rsquo; to the input port for your device, and Ardour's
&lsquo;MIDI control in&rsquo; to your device's output port.  Some
devices present a few different ports, and often the easiest way to
find the correct one is to connect them all, verify that things work,
and then disconnect them one by one to find the one that is required.
</para>


</section> <!-- Generic MIDI surfaces -->

</chapter>
