<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-editor-window" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>The editor window</title>
<indexterm><primary>editor</primary></indexterm>

<para>
A typical Ardour editor window is shown in <xref linkend="fig-typical-editor2"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-typical-editor2">
  <title>A typical editor window</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="diagrams/editor-summary&dia;" scale="100"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
This window is where audio and MIDI material can be viewed, edited and
manipulated.  It offers a view of your session as it progresses in
time, and allows the constituent parts (tracks, regions, playlists and
so on) to be manipulated.  The contents of the main body of the window
represent the session's tracks and busses, the functionality of which
is discussed in <xref linkend="ch-tracks-and-busses"/>.
</para>

<para>
The remainder of this chapter discusses the other parts of the editor window.
</para>

<section>
<title>The playhead</title>
<indexterm><primary>playhead</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The red vertical line with arrow heads at either end is the called the
&lsquo;playhead&rsquo;.  The playhead position is used in a few different ways,
but the most obvious is that it lies at the point in time at which
Ardour is currently playing back or recording (or would be, were play
or record to be started).  It is also used in some editing operations,
as we will discuss later.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>The toolbar</title>
<indexterm><primary>toolbar</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The toolbar is a set of buttons that change the way the mouse and
keyboard interact with the regions on the tracks, in order to perform
different tasks.
</para>

<xref linkend="fig-toolbar-annotated"/> shows the buttons on the toolbar.

<figure id="fig-toolbar-annotated">
  <title>The Ardour toolbar</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="diagrams/toolbar-annotated&dia;"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
We will examine the broad function of these tools here, and go into
more detail on their operation later.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Select/move objects</emphasis> (<keycap>o</keycap>) &mdash; used to mark
  regions or MIDI notes as &lsquo;selected&rsquo;, and to move them around (in
  time, or to a different track, or to a different note in the case of
  MIDI).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Smart mode</emphasis> &mdash; this provides a combination of the
  functionality of &lsquo;select/move objects&rsquo; and &lsquo;select/move ranges&rsquo;
  which may be familiar to users of Pro Tools.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Select/move ranges</emphasis> (<keycap>r</keycap>) &mdash; used to mark
  ranges of time and to manipulate them.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Zoom range</emphasis> (<keycap>z</keycap>) &mdash; this provides a mode whereby a time
  range can be dragged with the mouse, and the editor window will zoom
  to show that time range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Region gain</emphasis> (<keycap>g</keycap>) &mdash; used to edit audio
  gain curves on regions.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Stretch/shrink</emphasis> (<keycap>t</keycap>) &mdash; allows stretching
  or shrinking of regions in time (using time-stretching /
  pitch-shifting algorithms) or MIDI notes.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Listen</emphasis> &mdash; used to listen from the start of a region,
  or to listen at varying speed and direction.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Draw/edit MIDI notes</emphasis> &mdash; used to draw new MIDI notes
  into MIDI regions, or change the length of those that are already
  there.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Edit region contents</emphasis> (<keycap>e</keycap>) &mdash; this is a
  kind of &lsquo;modifier&rsquo; for the other tools.  When selected, it means
  that the other tools will operate on region contents rather
  than the regions themselves.  For example, the select/move tool will
  select and move MIDI notes rather than the regions that the notes
  are in.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section>
<title>Rulers</title>

The rulers section of the editor gives the option of several views;
some time indications, in different units, details of tempo and meter
(time signature) changes, and a display of various types of marker.

Right-clicking over the marker area offers a menu from which the
displayed rulers can be chosen.

<section>
<title>Time displays</title>

The time rulers that can be displayed are:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Min:Sec</emphasis> &mdash; time in hours:minutes:seconds:millseconds.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Timecode</emphasis> &mdash; time in hours:minutes:seconds:frames.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Samples</emphasis> &mdash; time in audio samples.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Bars:Beats</emphasis> &mdash; time in bars and beats.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section>
<title>Meter and tempo</title>

Ardour provides support for considering a piece of music as having
tempo and meter.  This is optional in the sense that you can happily
ignore tempo and meter settings if they are not relevant to your
recording situation.

Use of tempo has two main effects; firstly, Ardour can provide a
metronome &lsquo;click&rsquo; which can be used as reference to record to.
Secondly, tempo will affect the speed at which MIDI data is played
back, so you can change how your records will sound by changing the
tempo.

Meter (time signature) also affects the metronome click, as the click
will emphasise the sound of the first beat of the bar.  It has no
effect on the <emphasis>playback</emphasis> of MIDI, but adjusting time signature to
match the music may make things more intuitive to work with.

Both tempo and meter affect the grid that is displayed (and,
optionally, snapped to) which shows bars and beats.  The grid will
adjust itself to zoom level, so the finer details of the session may
not be visible if you are zoomed too far out.
</section>

<section id="sec-markers">
<title>Markers</title>

<para>
Ardour supports a variety of markers for various purposes.  Markers
can either be a single point in time or a range of time.
</para>

<para>
The basic marker types for general purpose use are <emphasis>location
markers</emphasis> and <emphasis>range markers</emphasis>.  Location markers are
a point in time, and range markers represent, as one might expect, a
time range.
</para>

<para>
The &lsquo;start&rsquo; and &lsquo;end&rsquo; location markers are special.
They mark the start and end of the session.  They cannot be removed or renamed.
</para>

<para>
There are some other special marker types.  CD markers are intended to
indicate track marks for CD productions.  If a session has CD markers
at the start of each track, Ardour can generate a table-of-contents
for use with audio exports to allow them to be burnt to CD correctly.
</para>

<para>
Two special range markers are the &lsquo;loop&rsquo; and &lsquo;punch&rsquo; ranges.  The loop
range can be played back in a loop when the <emphasis>play loop
range</emphasis> button is clicked.  The punch range will be used with
punch-in recording.
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Clocks</title>

<para>
This area contains two clocks, the primary and secondary.  They both
show the location of the playhead, but can be set to different time
representations.  By default, for example, the primary clock shows
position as a time-code, and the secondary shows bars, beats and
ticks.
</para>

<para>
Right-clicking on a clock pops up a menu from which you can choose the
time representation from one of the following:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Timecode</emphasis> &mdash; shows time as
  hours:minutes:seconds:frames.  The number of frames per second is
  set by the session property &lsquo;timecode frames-per-second&rsquo; (see
  <xref linkend="sec-session-properties-timecode"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Bars:Beats</emphasis> &mdash; shows time as
  bars|beats|text|ticks (there are 1920 ticks per beat).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Minutes:Seconds</emphasis> &mdash; shows time as
  hours:minutes:seconds:milliseconds.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Samples</emphasis> &mdash; shows time as samples (according to the
  sampling rate that JACK is using).
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
In addition to the time, the clock shows some other information.
</para>

<para>
When set to &lsquo;timecode&rsquo;, the clock also shows the timecode reference
source; this defaults to &lsquo;INT&rsquo; for internal, but can also be &lsquo;JACK&rsquo; if
JACK is the timecode reference, &lsquo;MTC&rsquo; if Ardour is syncing to MIDI
time-code or &lsquo;M-Clock&rsquo; if Ardour is synced to MIDI clock.  To the
right of the timecode reference is the number of frames per second
(suffixed by &lsquo;D&rsquo;) if drop-frame is being used.
</para>

<para>
In &lsquo;Bars:Beats&rsquo; mode, the area underneath the time shows the tempo (in
beats per minute) and time signature that are currently in effect.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Times area</title>

<para>
The times area of the editor window shows a few useful bits of
information about any current selection and punch in/out range.  The
&lsquo;selection&rsquo; area shows the start, end and length of anything that is
currently selected (which may be a set of regions, a time range, or
whatever).  The &lsquo;punch&rsquo; area shows the punch range, and also whether
punch in and punch out are enabled; clicking &lsquo;In&rsquo; or &lsquo;Out&rsquo; will enable
punch in and out respectively, and the buttons will turn red in colour
to indicate that the corresponding punch is switched on.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-edit-point-selector">
<title>Edit point selector</title>
<indexterm><primary>edit point</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The &lsquo;edit point&rsquo; is a point in time within the session that is used
for a variety of different editing operations.  The edit point
selector is used to choose where the edit point should be; it can be
either at the playhead, at the selected marker or at the
mouse pointer position.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Zoom controls</title>
<indexterm><primary>zoom</primary></indexterm>

The zoom controls are shown in <xref linkend="fig-zoom-controls"/>.

<figure id="fig-zoom-controls"> 
  <title>The zoom controls</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="diagrams/zoom-controls&dia;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The zoom in and out controls zoom the editor window in and out in
terms of time; the &lsquo;zoom to session&rsquo; button zooms the editor window so
that the whole session is visible.  The &lsquo;zoom focus button&rsquo; selects
a reference point to decide which part of the session the editor window
should display after the zoom.  These reference points are as follows:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Left</emphasis> &mdash; the left-hand side of the editor
window remains at the same point in time.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Right</emphasis> &mdash; the right-hand side of the editor
window remains at the same point in time.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Center</emphasis> &mdash; the centre of the editor window
remains at the same point in time.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Playhead</emphasis> &mdash; the playhead will be kept in the
centre of the editor window (where possible).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Mouse</emphasis> &mdash; the point of the session that the
mouse pointer is over will be kept at the same point in the editor
window.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Edit point</emphasis> &mdash; the current edit point will be
used as a reference.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Grid controls</title>
<indexterm><primary>grid</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Ardour has an optional &lsquo;grid&rsquo; which can be used to align things
precisely in time.  The grid can either be disabled (by choosing &lsquo;No
Grid&rsquo; from the drop-down box), fully enabled (&lsquo;Grid&rsquo;) or &lsquo;Magnetic&rsquo;.
When the grid is fully enabled, any object that is moved (regions,
MIDI notes or automation points, for example) will be forcibly snapped
to the grid.  In &lsquo;magnetic&rsquo; mode, it is possible to move things off
the grid, but when they get close to a grid intersection they will be
snapped.
</para>

<para>
Next to the grid on/off drop-down box is a selector for the interval
to snap to.  There are a large variety of options here, most of which
are self explanatory.  &lsquo;Region starts/ends/syncs/bounds&rsquo; snaps to
various parts of existing regions, which can be useful when alignment
needs to be relative to existing material rather than some arbitrary
grid.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Nudge controls</title>
<indexterm><primary>nudge</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The nudge controls allow objects to be &lsquo;nudged&rsquo;, or moved by a fixed
amount backward or forward.  The left and right buttons move currently
selected things either backward or forward in time, and the small
clock to the left of these buttons sets the amount of time to nudge
by.  As with all other clocks, you can right-click on the clock to
choose the time representation you want to use.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>The editor lists</title>

<para>
At the right of the editor is an optional area which provides one of a
range of useful lists of parts of your session.  The list can be
hidden or shown using the <guimenuitem>Show Editor List</guimenuitem>
option from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.  The very right-hand
side of the list gives a selection of tabs which are used to choose
the list to view.  The left-hand border of the list can be dragged to
vary the width of the list.
</para>

<section xml:id="sec-region-list"><title>Region list</title>
<indexterm><primary>region list</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The region list shows all the regions in the session.  The left-hand
column gives the region name, and there are a range of times given for
information.  At the right of the list are four columns of flags that can be altered:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>L</emphasis> &mdash; whether the region position is locked, so that it
  cannot be moved.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>G</emphasis> &mdash; whether the region's position is &lsquo;glued&rsquo; to bars
  and beats.  If so, the region will stay at the same position in bars
  and beats even if the tempo and/or time signature change.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>M</emphasis> &mdash; whether the region is muted, so that it will not be heard.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>O</emphasis> &mdash; whether the region is opaque; opaque regions
  &lsquo;block&rsquo; regions below them from being heard, whereas &lsquo;transparent&rsquo;
  regions have their contents mixed with whatever is underneath.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Hovering the mouse pointer over a column heading shows a tool-tip
which can be handy to remember what the columns are for.
</para>

<para>
A handy feature of the region list is that its regions can be dragged
and dropped into a suitable track in the session.
</para>

</section> <!-- Region list -->

<section>
<title>Tracks &amp; Busses</title>

<para>
This lists the tracks and busses that are present in the session.  The
list order reflects the order in the editor, and you can drag-and-drop
track or bus names in the editor list to re-order them in the editor.
The columns in the list can all be clicked to alter the track/bus
state, and they represent the following:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem> <emphasis>V</emphasis> &mdash; whether the track or bus is visible; they can be
  hidden, in which case they will still play, but just not be visible
  in the editor; this can be useful for keeping the display uncluttered.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>A</emphasis> &mdash; whether the track or bus is active; unactive
  tracks will not play, and will not consume any CPU.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>I</emphasis> &mdash; for MIDI tracks, whether the MIDI input is
  enabled; this dictates whether MIDI data from the track's inputs
  ports will be passed through the track.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>R</emphasis> &mdash; whether the track is record-enabled.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>M</emphasis> &mdash; whether the track is muted.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>S</emphasis> &mdash; track solo state.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>SI</emphasis> &mdash; track solo-isolated state.
</listitem><listitem> <emphasis>SS</emphasis> &mdash; solo safe state.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
As with the region list, hovering the mouse pointer over a column
heading shows a tool-tip which can be handy to remember what the
columns are for.
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Snapshots</title>
<indexterm><primary>snapshot</primary></indexterm>

<para>
This list gives the snapshots that exist of this session.  Clicking on
a snapshot name will load that snapshot.
</para>

</section> <!-- Tracks & Busses -->

<section><title>Track &amp; Bus Groups</title>

<para>
This shows the track/bus groups that exist in the session.  These
groups allow related tracks to share various properties (such as mute
or record enable state).  For full details, see
<xref linkend="sec-track-and-bus-groups"/>.
</para>

<para>
The columns in this list are as follows:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Col</emphasis> &mdash; the colour that the group uses for its tab in the editor.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Name</emphasis> &mdash; the group name.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>V</emphasis> &mdash; whether the tracks and busses in the group are visible.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>On</emphasis> &mdash; whether the group is enabled.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>G</emphasis> &mdash; ticked if the constituents of the group are sharing gain settings.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Rel</emphasis> &mdash; ticked if shared gains are relative.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>M</emphasis> &mdash; ticked if the constituents share mute status.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>S</emphasis> &mdash; ticked if the constituents share solo status.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Rec</emphasis> &mdash; ticked if the constituents share record-enable status.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Mon</emphasis> &mdash; whether the constituents share monitor settings.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Sel</emphasis> &mdash; whether the constituents are selected together.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>E</emphasis> &mdash; whether edits to the constituents are performed to all others.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>A</emphasis> &mdash; whether the constituents share active status.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section> <!-- Track & Bus Groups -->

<section>
<title>Ranges &amp; Marks</title>

This lists the ranges and markers that exist in the session, and
allows them to be edited.  First, there is the current loop and punch
range; there are three clocks, being the start of the range, the end
of the range and the length of the range.  The start and end points
have a &lsquo;Use PH&rsquo; button beside them, which you can click to set the
corresponding position using the current position of the playhead.

Following this is a list of the session's markers, and finally there
is a list of the range markers.

At the bottom of the list are buttons to add new markers or ranges.

The <guibutton>-</guibutton> button beside each marker and range
allows that particular mark to be removed.

</section> <!-- Ranges & Marks -->
</section> <!-- The editor lists -->

<section><title>Other buttons</title>

<para>
The editor window contains a few other buttons, which are described here.
</para>

<section>
<title>Solo</title>
<para>
This button flashes red if any tracks are soloed, and you can click it
to turn off all solos.
</para>
</section> <!-- Solo -->

<section>
<title>Feedback</title>
<indexterm><primary>feedback</primary></indexterm>

<para>
It is possible to connect things up so that there are feedback loops;
a simple example might be connecting the output of a track to its
input, but obviously there are much more convoluted arrangements
possible.  Ardour detects any feedback that exists, and will keep its
signal processing pathways in the state they were in just before the
feedback was introduced.  If Ardour is doing this, it flashes the
feedback button to let you know that the routing in effect may not be
what the user interface is showing.  You should remove the feedback
path, upon which this light will stop flashing.
</para>

<!-- XXX
Metronome
Audition}
Internal
Auto Play
Auto Return
-->

</section> <!-- Feedback -->

<section xml:id="sec-positional-sync-button"><title>Positional sync button</title>

<para>
The positional sync button is located to the left of the clocks, and
initially marked <guilabel>Internal</guilabel> to indicate that Ardour
is not synchronising to anything else.  Clicking this button will
enable synchronisation to the source configured in the
<guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> dialogue.  See <xref linkend="ch-synchronisation"/>.
</para>

</section> <!-- Positional sync button -->

</section> <!-- Other Buttons -->

<section>
<title>The transport controls</title>

Ardour uses the term &lsquo;transport&rsquo; in a sense that might be similar to
those who have used tape machines.  The transport is said to be
&lsquo;moving&rsquo; (or &lsquo;rolling&rsquo;, as with tape) when Ardour is playing back or
recording, and &lsquo;stopped&rsquo; when it is not.  The transport can be
controlled using the buttons shown in
<xref linkend="fig-transport-controls2"/>.

<figure id="fig-transport-controls2"> 
  <title>Main transport controls</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/transport-controls&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

From left to right, these controls are:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/midi-panic&scs;"/> &mdash;
  <emphasis>MIDI panic</emphasis> &mdash; click this to send note-offs and reset
  controller messages on all MIDI channels.  This is useful if, for
  example, when a MIDI synthesizer has a stuck note and you want to silence
  it.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/go-to-start&scs;"/> &mdash;
  <emphasis>Start of session</emphasis> &mdash; moves the playhead to the session
  start marker.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/go-to-end&scs;"/> &mdash; <emphasis>End
of session</emphasis> &mdash; moves the playhead to the session end
marker.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/loop&scs;"/> &mdash; <emphasis>Play
loop</emphasis> &mdash; this starts playback in looped mode, so that
the current loop range will be played repeatedly.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/play-range&scs;"/> &mdash;
<emphasis>Play range or selection</emphasis> &mdash; if there is a
selected time range, it will be played back.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/play&scs;"/> &mdash;
<emphasis>Play</emphasis> &mdash; this starts playback of the session
from wherever the playhead currently is (in other words, it sets the
transport &lsquo;rolling&rsquo;, or moving)
</listitem>
<listitem> 
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/stop&scs;"/> &mdash;
<emphasis>Stop</emphasis> &mdash; this stops playback or record.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<imagedata fileref="screenshots/session-record&scs;"/> &mdash;
<emphasis>Record</emphasis> &mdash; if this is clicked so that it
flashes red, Ardour will record onto record-enabled tracks when the
transport is moving.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-summary">
<title>The summary</title>
<indexterm><primary>summary</primary></indexterm>

<para>
The summary area of the editor window gives an overview of your entire
session.  No matter how long the session is, or how many tracks it
has, the summary will arrange itself so that the entire session is
drawn within it.  Inside the summary tracks are represented as
light-grey bars, regions as coloured bars, the playhead as a vertical
red line and the session start and end markers as vertical yellow
lines.  On top of the summary is drawn a light-grey translucent box
(the &lsquo;view box&rsquo;) which indicates the part of the session that is
currently visible in the main part of the editor window.
</para>

<para>
The summary is intended for two main purposes: firstly, to get an idea
of the whole session at a glance, and secondly to navigate around it
easily.  You can use the summary to do the following things:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Dragging the view box around will move the view of the session
  in the main editor window.
</listitem>
<listitem>Resizing the view box (by clicking and dragging on its edges)
  will zoom into or out of the session.
</listitem>
<listitem>Clicking with <keycap>&modtwo;</keycap> held down will move
the playhead to the click position.
</listitem>
<listitem>Clicking with <keycap>&modtertiary;</keycap> held down will
centre the editor's view at the click position.
</listitem>
<listitem>Moving the mouse's scroll-wheel will scroll the editor's view.
</listitem>
<listitem>Moving the mouse's scroll-wheel with <keycap>&modone;</keycap> held down will
  zoom the editor's view in or out.
</listitem>
<listitem>Moving the mouse's scroll-wheel with <keycap>&modtwo;</keycap> held down will
  scroll the editor's view left or right.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

The left, right, up and down buttons to either side of the summary
allow the editor window to be scrolled in each direction.

<section>
<title>The status bar</title>

This contains the following things:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>File</emphasis> &mdash; the type of file that Ardour is using to record audio;
this can be change from the <guilabel>Media</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties dialogue</guilabel> (see <xref linkend="sec-session-properties-media"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>JACK</emphasis> &mdash; the sampling rate that JACK (and therefore Ardour) is
 using, and the duration of one JACK period.
</listitem>
<listitem>
 <emphasis>Buffers</emphasis> &mdash; how full the &lsquo;playback buffers&rsquo; are (prefixed &lsquo;p&rsquo;),
  and how empty the &lsquo;capture buffers&rsquo; (prefixed &lsquo;c&rsquo;).  The playback
  buffers are areas of memory that Ardour uses to store audio and MIDI
  data while it is being passed from the disk to the audio outputs;
  Ardour tries to keep them full (so that there is always data
  available for playback), but if you have a lot of tracks and (or)
  slow disks, Ardour may not be able to keep up.  The closer the
  playback buffer number is to 100%, the better.  Similarly, as data
  is being captured for record, Ardour tries to write it to disk; if
  it cannot write the data quickly enough, the record buffers will
  fill and problems will occur.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<indexterm><primary>DSP</primary></indexterm><emphasis>DSP</emphasis>
&mdash; an estimate of the amount of time that Ardour is spending
doing digital signal processing (DSP) of your session.  If this gets
near 100% it indicates that your system is being overloaded, and you
may get glitches or &lsquo;pops&rsquo; in your audio.  First steps to fixing this
are:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
Reduce the number of plugins you are using (especially complicated ones like reverbs).
</listitem>
<listitem>
&lsquo;Freeze&rsquo; some tracks.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Increase JACK's buffer size.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Get a faster computer!
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sidebar>
<para>
Every time JACK calls Ardour, to give it audio from inputs and take
away audio from outputs, Ardour has until the next JACK call to do its
processing.  The DSP load is the percentage of this available time
that Ardour is taking up.  More than 100% means that Ardour will not
have performed one lot of processing before JACK asks it to do more,
so the system is critically overloaded.  As suggested above, one can
increase Ardour's chances of getting everything finished by increasing
the period between JACK's calls (by increasing the JACK buffer size),
or by reducing the amount of time Ardour requires to do its work (by
reducing plugin count, or using faster hardware).
</para>

<para>
Note that DSP load will probably not vary predictably with CPU speed.
Many other things are involved in the timing of the sound-card / JACK
/ Ardour interaction; including the real-time performance of your
system and kernel, the details of your hardware, and in some cases
blind (good or bad) luck.
</para>
</sidebar>

</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Disk</emphasis> &mdash; the amount of time for which you can record (on the
  tracks that are currently record-enabled) given the amount of disk
  space you have available.  If no tracks are record-enabled, the time
  remaining is computed assuming that you are recording one track.
</listitem>
<listitem>
And finally, the time (using the 24-hour clock), just in case you have somewhere to be.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The various parts of the status bar can be shown or hidden by
right-clicking and choosing the elements that you want to see.  This
can be useful for reducing the editor window's width for use on small
screens.
</para>

</section>
</section>
</chapter>
