<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Hello, and welcome to Ardour!
</para>

<section>
<title>What is Ardour?</title>

<para>
Ardour is an open-source digital audio workstation (DAW) for Linux and
Mac OS X.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Typographical conventions</title>

<para>
This manual uses special symbols to denote sections which contain
advanced material.  The reader can skip these sections without any
great loss.
</para>

<sidebar>
<para>
Tricky parts of the text are formatted like this.  They contain extra
information which may be of interest to advanced users.
</para>
</sidebar>

</section>




<section>
<title>About this manual</title>

<para>
This manual is a work-in-progress.  In other words, it is not even
close to being complete.  Any suggestions for improvements, content,
or comments on parts that do not make sense are welcome to
<ulink url="mailto:cth@carlh.net">cth@carlh.net</ulink>.
</para>

<sidebar>
<para>
For those familiar with &lsquo;git&rsquo;, the manual's DocBook source can be
obtained from the git repository linked from <ulink
url="http://carlh.net/ardour">http://carlh.net/ardour</ulink>.
Patches to the manual are most welcome.
</para>
</sidebar>

<section><title>Licence</title>

<para>
This manual is licensed under a Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.  Please see
<ulink
url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ulink>
for a human-readable summary of what this means.
</para>

<imagedata fileref="graphics/cc.png"/>

</section>


</section> <!-- About this manual -->

<section>
<title>Getting help with Ardour</title>

<para>
There are several places that you can get help with using Ardour.
</para>


<section>
<title>The website</title>

<para>
Ardour's website (<ulink url="http://ardour.org/">http://ardour.org</ulink>) contains many
useful resources, including a list of frequently-asked questions, a
forum and a bug and feature request tracker.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>IRC</title>
<indexterm><primary>IRC</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Ardour's core developers and several key users are usually to be found
on Internet Relay Chat (IRC) on <ulink url="irc://irc.freenode.net">irc.freenode.net</ulink> in #ardour and
#ardour-osx at pretty much any hour of the day or night.  This is a
live chat system that is great for dicussing Ardour's development,
design, and also user problems.  There are IRC clients for most
operating systems, or you can join in directly from your web browser
by choosing <guimenuitem>Chat</guimenuitem> from the Ardour's <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.
</para>

<para>
If you join the IRC rooms, here are a few tips:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Don't ask to ask, just ask</emphasis> &mdash; rather than saying &lsquo;Is it
  ok if I ask a question?&rsquo;, just ask your question &mdash; it is not
  considered rude to do so.  Then wait: your answer may come in
  seconds, minutes, hours or never, depending on who is around and
  what time of the day it is wherever they happen to be in the world.
  In particular, make sure you <emphasis>do</emphasis> wait; do not get upset if you
  don't get an answer straight away.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Don't be offended if no-one replies</emphasis> &mdash; although other
  users may be logged into the channel, they may well be coding
  Ardour, cooking, reading XKCD, cleaning their ostrabagalous devices,
  or any number of other things.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Don't paste large amounts of text into the
channel</emphasis> &mdash; if you have more than a couple of lines of
output from some command that you want to show everyone, use a site
like <olink url="http://pastebin/com">pastebin.com</olink> You can
copy your text into that site, and it will give you a web address that
you can paste into the channel.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Be as detailed as possible</emphasis> &mdash; if you have a problem,
  tell us what version of Ardour you are using, and what operating
  system you are running on (Linux, OS X or Windows).
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</section>


<section>
<title>Mailing lists</title>

There is a Ardour users mailing list, where various discussions about
Ardour (and recording in general) take place.  There are links to join
the list on Ardour's website.

</section>

<section>
<title>Support expectations</title>

<para>
As Ardour evolves, it becomes a serious alternative to commercial
products for more and more people. We see the download counts increase
for each new release, and the volume of traffic on the mailing lists
is growing. That's lovely, of course. We work on Ardour without the
accoutrements of a &lsquo;normal&rsquo; software corporation, so whenever a new
user finds our work useful and worthwile, it makes what we do seem
meaningful and worth continuing with.
</para>

<para>
Unfortunately, it's not all roses we receive.  With wider public
interest and more users, there's bound to be people who are
disappointed in Ardour. We believe, however, that it's only because
most newcomers do not realize what to expect.
</para>


<section>
<title>The development team</title>

<para>
Many users probably don't realize it, but the development team driving
Ardour forward is very small for the amazingly complex piece of
software that is a contemporary DAW.
</para>

<para>
At this time, the main force behind Ardour is delivered by one person,
with core aid from two others, and contributions from on the order of
a dozen others. Consider that we do support, web site maintenance,
documentation, feature enhancements, debugging, as well as
development.
</para>

<para>
There are more people (perhaps another dozen) pitching in with
translation, release engineering (preparing Ardour for users), Mantis
triaging (&lsquo;Mantis&rsquo; is the bug database used to keep track of known
problems, &lsquo;triaging&rsquo; the process of prioritizing and verifying bugs)
and other necessary tasks.
</para>

<para>
So we are always looking for new people to help, and while
(unfortunately) a common misconception is that a project like Ardour
would only benefit from more programmers, it is not the case! Whatever
your ability, we can use it. If you are interested in spending a
little time making Ardour a better DAW, please don't hesitate to join
the developer mailing list and offer your services.
</para>

</section>
<section>
<title>Ardour features and polish</title>

<para>
As Ardour is getting more powerful and usable, we attract more and
more users who expect the same feature set and product polish as
they'll find in a commercial product such as DigiDesign's ProTools or
Steinberg's Nuendo. This isn't the right way to think about Ardour at
this time.
</para>

<para>
Not that we don't want to get there, you understand, but it's simply
not a reasonable comparison. DigiDesign has spent who knows how many
man-hours worth of development on ProTools and can spend a lot on
getting good documentation written, new features, debugging,
installation process made smooth and generally polish the thing till
it shines. In comparison, Ardour development is driven primarily by
the interests of just a few people. Development is a full time job for
the lead developer, who also raises a three kids, fixes up his house,
has friends and even a relationship with a gorgeous woman.
</para>

<para>
Do not read that as an excuse for why Ardour lacks in comparison with
other products. Do read it as an explanation for why you should expect
nothing more from Ardour than it actually delivers. And rest assured
that the developers want and expect it to rival, or better yet, beat
the proprietary DAWs. That's why we're so committed to this
development model &mdash; because we believe it's the best way to get there.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Releases</title>

<para>
Ardour releases are also put together by volunteers. This means that
there's usually only prebuilt binaries available for a few select
platforms. While we would like to see Ardour prebuilt for all the
platforms (and operating system versions) Ardour runs on, it's simply
not possible since the volunteers doing the release only have access
to a subset of those platforms.
</para>

<para>
With specific regards to library dependencies: depending on the
volunteer's machine configuration, the Ardour binary may require you
to install additional or newer libraries before it will work. If so,
the installation instructions should contain the necessary information
for you to find those libraries. Please do not complain about the need
for these libraries &mdash; just as you might dislike installing/upgrading
the libraries, the volunteer doing the release may dislike
removing/downgrading the libraries on her machine.
</para>

<para>
If you find that there are no prebuilt binaries for your
platform/configuration, and are willing to help provide packages for
coming releases, please join the developer mailing list and offer your
services. It is not a requirement that you are a programmer, but there
may be a requirement for (commercial) development tools which not
everyone would have access to. If you have the time and tools, we can
probably guide you through the process, even if you don't have the
knowledge.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Support</title>

<para>
You can join both the user and developer mailing lists and ask
questions there. You can also ask for help on IRC, and you can file
bug reports and feature requests in Mantis. However, since support is
also provided on a volunteer basis, you must be careful not to have
unreasonable expectations: you cannot demand your questions to be
answered or bugs to be fixed. In short: the people volunteering time
to Ardour only have so much time available, and they alone decide how
to spend it. Please respect their choice.
</para>

<para>
When that is said, you should know that the mailing list and the IRC
channel are friendly places &mdash; few requests go without reply. And we
also do our best to fix all bugs reported, just as we strive to
implement requested features. But as should be evident from the number
of open bugs in Mantis, there's not enough hours in the day to allow
us to address all issues in a timely manner.
</para>

</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
