<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-locations-markers" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Locations and markers</title>
<indexterm><primary>locations</primary><primary>markers</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Ardour provides a few ways to mark up specific times or ranges of time
in your sessions.  These are displayed, and can be edited from the
rulers area of the editor window, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-typical-editor2"/>.
</para>

<para>
Markers are divided up into the following categories, each of which is
allotted a separate line in the rulers area:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Location markers</emphasis> &mdash; these mark a single
point in time.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Range markers</emphasis> &mdash; these mark a range of time.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Loop/punch ranges</emphasis> &mdash; these also mark a range
of time, but are specifically for use when looping (see <xref
linkend="sec-transport-controls"/> or punching (see <xref
linkend="sec-punch-in-out"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>CD markers</emphasis> &mdash; these can mark either a single
point in time or a range, and can be used to add track marks to
compact disc (CD) images; see <xref linkend="sec-cd-track-marks"/>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section>
<title>Location markers</title>

<para>
You can insert a location marker in a couple of ways; firstly, you can
right-click on the location markers ruler to display the menu (as
shown in <xref linkend="fig-location-markers-menu"/>) and then select
<guilabel>New location marker</guilabel>.  Alternatively, choose
<guilabel>Add Mark From Playhead</guilabel> from the
<guilabel>Markers</guilabel> submenu of the
<guilabel>Transport</guilabel> menu (or press <keycap>Enter</keycap>
on the numeric keypad) to put a new location marker at the current
playhead position.
</para>

<figure id="fig-location-markers-menu">
  <title>The location markers context menu</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/location-markers-menu&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Markers can be selected by left-clicking on them; this will draw a
blue line at the marker's position.  Additional markers can then be
selected by &modone;-clicking.  Selected markers can be dragged around
in time.
</para>

<para>
Several operations on markers are available by right-clicking them to
open the marker context menu.  From this menu, you can:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Locate to Here</emphasis> &mdash; move the playhead to this
marker's position.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Play from Here</emphasis> &mdash; start playback from this
marker's position.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Move Mark to Playhead</emphasis> &mdash; move this marker to
the current playhead position.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Create Range to Next Marker</emphasis> &mdash; create a
range marker between this location and the next one along on the
timeline.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Hide</emphasis> &mdash; hide this marker from the view.  It
can be re-shown from the <guilabel>Locations</guilabel> window (see
<xref linkend="sec-locations-window"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Rename</emphasis> &mdash; change the name of the marker.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Lock</emphasis> &mdash; if this is ticked, it will be
impossible to drag the marker's position; useful if you want to
prevent accidental movements.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Glue to Bars and Beats</emphasis> &mdash; if this is ticked,
the marker will maintain its position in bars and beats even if there
are changes in tempo and meter (see <xref linkend="sec-time"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Remove</emphasis> &mdash; removes the marker.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
There are also a few options on the <guilabel>Active Mark</guilabel>
submenu of the <guilabel>Transport</guilabel> menu.  These options
apply to the currently selected location marker, and move it to a
nearby region boundary, region sync point, or to the playhead or mouse.
</para>

</section> <!-- Location markers -->

<section>
<title>Range markers</title>

<para>
Range markers are somewhat similar to location markers, except that
they cover a range of time.  They might be useful for marking out
areas of a song (a chorus, perhaps).
</para>

<para>
Create a range marker by &modone;-dragging from one part of the range
markers ruler to another; when you release the mouse button, a range
marker will be created.  Either end of this marker can be moved around
with a drag.  &modone;-dragging one end of a range will move the other
end in the same way.
</para>

<para>
As with location markers, right-clicking on a range marker will offer
a menu of useful things that you can do with the marker.  Some of the
options operate on the range, and some on the start or end point
(depending on which end of the marker you clicked on to open the
menu).
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Play Range</emphasis> &mdash; play from the start to the end
of the range, then stop.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Locate to Range Mark</emphasis> &mdash; move the playhead to
the start or end of the range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Play from Range Mark</emphasis> &mdash; start playback from
the the start or end of the range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Loop Range</emphasis> &mdash; start looped playback of the range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Set Range Mark from Playhead</emphasis> &mdash; set the
start or end of the range to the playhead position.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Set Range from Range Selection</emphasis> &mdash; if you
have selected a time range using the select/move ranges tool
(<imagedata fileref="screenshots/tool-ranges&scs;"/>) this will set
this range marker to cover the selected time range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Zoom to Range</emphasis> &mdash; this zooms in so that the
time range of the marker (and a little either side) is displayed in
the editor.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Export Range&hellip;</emphasis> &mdash; this opens the
<guilabel>export</guilabel> dialogue and sets it up to export the
marker's time range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Hide Range</emphasis> &mdash;  hide this marker from the view.  It
can be re-shown from the <guilabel>Locations</guilabel> window (see
<xref linkend="sec-locations-window"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Rename Range&hellip;</emphasis> &mdash; change the name of the marker.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Separate Regions in Range</emphasis> &mdash; this will look
at any selected tracks, and split regions on those tracks at the start
and end of the range.  This has the effect of &lsquo;chopping&rsquo;
the sound within the range so that it can be copied, perhaps, or moved
elsewhere.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Select All in Range</emphasis> &mdash; this selects all
regions which lie wholly or partly within the marker's range.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Select Range</emphasis> &mdash; this selects the time range
of the marker, moving into select/move ranges mode (<imagedata
fileref="screenshots/tool-ranges&scs;"/>) if it is not already engaged.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section> <!-- Range markers -->

<section xml:id="sec-cd-track-marks">
<title>CD track marks</title>

<para>
If your session contains markers on the <guilabel>CD
Markers</guilabel> ruler, Ardour can export these as a TOC or CUE file
which can be used when burning a CD to indicate where the track marks
should be.  See <xref linkend="sec-ch-export"/> for more details on
exporting.
</para>

</section> <!-- CD and DVD track marks -->

<section xml:id="sec-locations-window">
<title>The locations window</title>

<para>
It may sometimes be useful to see details of a particular marker, or
of all the markers in the session.  This can be done in the
<guilabel>Locations</guilabel> window, opened from the
<guilabel>Window</guilabel> menu or by pressing
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>, as shown
in <xref linkend="fig-locations-window"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-locations-window">
  <title>The locations window</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/locations-window&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
In this window we see three distinct areas; these contain details of
the loop and punch ranges, the location markers and the range markers.
</para>

<para>
Each marker has a button to the left of its name which will remove the
marker.  The marker can be renamed by editing its name entry.
Location markers have a single clock which show the marker's position.
This clock can be edited to move the marker, or the <guilabel>Use
PH</guilabel> button will move the marker to the playhead position.
Range markers have three clocks, one each for start time, end time and
length.
</para>

<para>
Markers can be set up to be hidden, locked, or glued to bars and beats
using the appropriate checkboxes.  Finally, the two buttons at the
bottom of the window allow new location makers or ranges to be added
to the session.
</para>

</section> <!-- The locations window -->

</chapter>
