<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Quick start</title>

<!-- XXX: links to things later on -->

<para>
This chapter blithely assumes that you just want to use Ardour to make
a basic audio recording from a sound card, and describes how that can
be achieved.  We assume that you have some sound source (such as a
microphone, guitar or whatever) plugged into one of your sound card's
inputs, and a monitoring system (speakers or headphones) connected to
its outputs.
</para>

<section>
<title>Starting Ardour and creating a session</title>

<para>
When Ardour is run for the first time, it starts with the dialogue box
shown in <xref linkend="fig-welcome-to-ardour"/>.  Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to continue.
</para>

<figure id="fig-welcome-to-ardour"> 
  <title>Welcome to Ardour!</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/welcome-to-ardour&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
As it is the first run, Ardour now asks a few basic questions about
how it should be set up.  Its first question is about where to put
sessions by default, as shown in
<xref linkend="fig-default-folder-for-new-sessions"/>.  The initial choice
will be the your home directory; other locations can be selected by
clicking on the button and selecting an alternative directory.
</para>

<figure id="fig-default-folder-for-new-sessions"> 
  <title>Default folder for new sessions</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/default-folder-for-new-sessions&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The next choice governs how Ardour will handle monitoring, as shown in
<xref linkend="fig-monitoring-choices"/>.  For the purposes of this
test, choose &lsquo;Ask Ardour to playback material as it is being
recorded'; this is probably the most widely-useful of the options.
More detail on monitoring options can be found in <xref
linkend="sec-monitoring"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-monitoring-choices"> 
  <title>Monitoring choices</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/monitoring-choices&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Following this, Ardour asks for a choice with respect to a monitor
section (see <xref linkend="fig-monitor-section"/>).  This is
explained in more detail in <xref linkend="sec-mute-and-solo"/>; for
now, just choose the default &lsquo;use a master bus directly&rsquo;.
</para>

<figure id="fig-monitor-section">
  <title>Monitor section</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/monitor-section&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
At this point, if JACK has not already been started, Ardour will try
to do it for you.  In order to do that, it asks about how JACK should
be set up (<xref linkend="fig-audio-midi-setup-device"/>).
</para>

<para>
There are three pages to the Audio / MIDI setup dialogue; the first is
&lsquo;device&rsquo;, which allows selection of the sound card that Ardour will
use, the sampling rate at which it will operate, and the buffer size.
For now, select the interface that you are using for recording and
leave other options as they are.  For more information on the options
here, consult <xref linkend="ch-jack"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-audio-midi-setup-device">
  <title>Audio/MIDI setup &mdash; device</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/audio-midi-setup-device&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The final step in creating our session is to give it a name, as in
<xref linkend="fig-new-session"/>.  Enter something like &lsquo;test&rsquo; and click
<guibutton>Open</guibutton>.  At last, the reward should be the editor window
(<xref linkend="fig-editor"/>).  The session is created!
</para>

<figure id="fig-new-session">
  <title>New session</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/new-session&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<figure id="fig-editor">
  <title>And finally: the editor!</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/editor&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

</section>
<section><title>Adding a track and connecting it up</title>

<para>
The next step is to add a track to our session so that we have
something to record onto.  Choose <guimenuitem>Add Track or
Bus&hellip;</guimenuitem> from <guimenu>Track</guimenu> at the top of
the editor window.  This will bring up a dialogue box, as shown in
<xref linkend="fig-quickstart-add-track-or-bus"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-quickstart-add-track-or-bus">
  <title><guilabel>Add Track or Bus</guilabel> dialogue</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/add-track-or-bus&scs;" scale="50"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
For now, leave the options as they are; this will create a single
monophonic audio track.  This track must now be connected to the sound
card so that it can record incoming audio.
</para>

<para>
Perhaps the easiest way to connect up this new track is to open its
editor mixer strip.  Do this now by pressing
<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo> or choosing <guimenuitem>Show Editor
Mixer</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.  The top of
the mixer strip that appears looks like that in <xref
linkend="fig-top-of-mixer-strip"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-top-of-mixer-strip">
  <title>Top part of a mixer strip</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/top-of-mixer-strip&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
At the top of this mixer strip there are three main buttons.  The
first, labelled &lsquo;Audio 1&rsquo; (the name of the track) can be clicked on to
open a menu of options for the track.  The second, marked &lsquo;1&rsquo; is the
input selector, and the third, marked &phgr;, is a button to invert
the track's signal.
</para>

<para>
In order to look at the connections to the input of this track,
left-click on the button marked &lsquo;1&rsquo; to open the input <emphasis>port
matrix</emphasis>, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-input-port-matrix"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-input-port-matrix">
  <title>Input port matrix</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/input-port-matrix&scs;" scale="40"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The port matrix is the main interface that Ardour offers for
connecting things together.  In our example matrix, the left-hand side
shows a set of ports that generate audio data; these correspond to the
sound card inputs, outputs of Ardour busses and tracks, and other
things that may exist on the system.  Different groups of these ports
can be seen by choosing one of the tabs on the far left-hand side of
the dialogue.
</para>

<para>
At the bottom of the dialogue is the input to our track.
</para>

<para>
In the example matrix, there is a green dot at the intersection of the
&lsquo;L&rsquo; part of &lsquo;in 1+2&rsquo; and the &lsquo;Audio 1
in&rsquo; port.  This means that the input of the &lsquo;Audio
1&rsquo; track hardware input 1.  Change this connection, if
necessary, by clicking on the square which corresponds to the input to
record from.  At this point, the Audio 1 meter should display any
signal that is being sent into the sound card.  If this is not
working, something has gone wrong.
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Recording</title>

<para>
At this point, Ardour is receiving a signal from some external sound
source via the sound card.  It is now possible to make a test
recording.  Click the record-enable buttons (red buttons with a pink
circle) in both the &lsquo;Audio 1&rsquo; track controls and the main transport
controls (shown in <xref linkend="fig-track-controls"/> and
<xref linkend="fig-transport-controls"/>), then click &lsquo;Play&rsquo; to start
the transport.
</para>

<figure id="fig-track-controls">
  <title>Track controls area</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/track-controls&scs;" scale="50"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<figure id="fig-transport-controls">
  <title>Main transport controls</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/transport-controls&scs;" scale="60"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Ardour is now recording; the playhead will move, and a red rectangle
will be drawn where the recording is taking place.  Make a noise with
your external sound source!  When you have finished recording, click
the Stop button in the transport controls area.  You should now have a
region containing your recording on the &lsquo;Audio 1&rsquo; track, as in
<xref linkend="fig-recorded-one-region"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-recorded-one-region">
  <title>Editor window after recording a region</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/recorded-one-region&scs;" scale="50"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

</section>

<section>
<title>Playing back your recording</title>

<para>
Now we can play back the audio that you have just recorded.  First,
you will need to move the playhead back to a point before your
recorded region.  Perhaps the easiest way to do this is to click
somewhere within the rulers area of the editor window (as shown in <xref linkend="sec-editor-window"/>).
</para>

<para>
Once the playhead is located before your recording, click the &lsquo;Play&rsquo;
button (or press the spacebar on the keyboard) to start playback.  You
should hear your recording through your monitor speakers or
headphones.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adding another track as an overdub</title>

<para>
Now we can experiment further by adding an overdub to the first
recording.  First, add a new track, as we did before, and connect it
up to the input on your soundcard which your source is connected to.
</para>

<para>
Now, record-enable the new track, move the playhead to before the
previously recorded region, make sure the session is record-enabled
and start the transport (by clicking &lsquo;Play&rsquo; or pressing the spacebar).
You should hear the previously-recorded audio on your monitor system
while the new recording is in progress.  Record something suitable
over the top of your first region.
</para>

<para>
We now have two tracks of recorded data; you might like to add some
more!
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Mix-down</title>

<para>
We will now assume that you want to do a mix-down of your magnum opus
into a stereo WAV file.  Such a file could later be converted to an
MP3, or burned to CD, or simply played-back as-is by some other media
player on your computer.  
</para>

<para>
First, we need to mix the tracks that you have recorded so that they
sound as you want them to.  We will cover much more advanced mixing
and processing later, but for now we will just set the relative levels
of the two tracks.  The easiest way to do this is to open the
<emphasis>mixer</emphasis> window, either by selecting
<guimenuitem>Mixer</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>Window</guimenu>
menu or by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>M</keycap></keycombo>.  The mixer window is
shown in <xref linkend="fig-mixer-window"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-mixer-window"> 
  <title>The mixer window</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/mixer&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Here you will see a mixer strip for each track that you have recorded,
and a &lsquo;master&rsquo; strip.  The signals for each track flow from the
recordings on disk, through the appropriate strip, and they are then
mixed together and passed through the master strip.  The bottom half
of each mixer strip contains a <emphasis>fader</emphasis>; this controls the level
of each track.  You can adjust the levels of each of your recordings
by dragging the mixer strip; the green marker indicates 0dBFS (&lsquo;unity
gain&rsquo;), at which the level of the track will be unaltered from the
recording.
</para>

<para>
Play back your recordings from the editor window, and experiment with
the levels in the mixer window until you have a sound that you are
happy with.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Export</title>

<para>
The final step is to export our recording into a stereo WAV file.
Ardour's export options are extensive, but for now we will keep it
simple.  Choose <guimenuitem>Export to Audio Files</guimenuitem> from
the <guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem> submenu of the
<guimenu>Session</guimenu> menu, and the <guilabel>Export</guilabel>
dialogue will open, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-export-dialogue"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-export-dialogue">
  <title>The export dialogue</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/export-dialogue&scs;" scale="35"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
First, we have to specify the format that we will export in.  Fill in
the <guilabel>preset label</guilabel> field with some name like &lsquo;WAV for CD&rsquo;, then click
the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button beside the Format entry in the dialogue, and
click on <guibutton>CD</guibutton>, <guibutton>Lossless (linear PCM)</guibutton>, <guibutton>WAV</guibutton> and
<guibutton>44.1kHz</guibutton> entries.  Then click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> to save the export
preset.  Enter some label for the export in the <emphasis>Location</emphasis>
section, then click <guibutton>Export</guibutton>.  Ardour will mix your session
down to a WAV file and save it in the <code>export</code> subdirectory of
your session folder.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
