<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Recording</title>

<section><title>Basic recording</title>

<para>
Basic recording in Ardour is pretty simple, both for audio and MIDI:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
Record-enable the track or tracks that you want to record to using the
<imagedata scale="50" fileref="screenshots/track-record&scs;"/>
button.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Record-enable the session using the <imagedata scale="50"
fileref="screenshots/session-record&scs;"/> button.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Put the playhead at the point at which you want to start recording.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Start the transport rolling using the <imagedata scale="50"
fileref="screenshots/play&scs;"/> button.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Stop the transport when you have finished using the <imagedata
scale="50" fileref="screenshots/stop&scs;"/> button.
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
This will result in new regions being added to the record-enabled
tracks, placed over the top of anything that is already there.  Note
that any previous regions are not deleted, simply hidden.  The
recorded data will be written to disk in the format configured in the
<guilabel>Media</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> (see <xref
linkend="sec-session-properties-media"/>).
</para>

<para>
It is not necessary to set up record-enable status with the transport
stopped; it can also be done while it is moving.  So, for example, it
is fine to start playback and then drop into record (either for the
whole session or just for a particular track) by pressing the
appropriate record enable.  Note that both session and track record
enable must be turned on (or &lsquo;armed&rsquo;) for recording to
happen.
</para>

<para>
Ardour will always play back any non-record-enabled tracks while you
are recording, so that you can listen to existing tracks whilst
playing new ones.  Ardour may also make the incoming audio and/or MIDI
audible, depending on the monitoring setup (see <xref
linkend="sec-monitoring"/>)
</para>

</section> <!-- Basic recording -->

<section><title>Punch in/out</title>

<para>
Often it is necessary to record over a small section of an existing
recording, perhaps to fix a mistake, or re-do a solo.  There are a few
approaches to this.  Most simply, you can start recording (or drop
into record) a little before the section that you want to change, and
stop a little after, then edit the resulting regions afterwards to fit
the new section into the old.
</para>

<para>
An alternative it to use &lsquo;punch-in&rsquo;.  With this mode,
Ardour will start and stop the recording for you.  You can set a punch
range, and then start the transport at any point before it.  When the
punch range starts, Ardour will start recording, and then it will stop
at the end of the range.
</para>

<para>
To set up a punch recording:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Set up the punch range</emphasis> &mdash; first, make sure
the &lsquo;loop/punch ranges&rsquo; ruler is displayed; if not,
right-click over the ruler bar and select
<guimenuitem>Loop/Punch</guimenuitem>.  Then, &modone;-drag the punch
range over the loop/punch ranges ruler.  When you finish the drag, a
menu will pop up; choose <guimenuitem>Set Punch Range</guimenuitem>.
This will put a punch range marker into the ruler; you can drag either
end of it to alter its position (see <xref linkend="fig-punch-range-marker"/>).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Enable punch in and out</emphasis> &mdash; click the
<guibutton>In</guibutton> and <guibutton>Out</guibutton> buttons in
the <guilabel>Punch</guilabel> section towards the right of Ardour's
top toolbar (see <xref linkend="fig-punch-in-out-buttons"/>).  At this
point the punch range will be coloured red in the editor window.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Record-enable the session and the tracks you want to punch on</emphasis>.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Start the transport</emphasis> at some point before the
punch range &mdash; the session will roll toward the punch range with
the session record-enable button flashing, and then go into record at
the start of the punch range.
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<figure id="fig-punch-range-marker"> 
  <title>A punch range marker</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/punch-range-marker&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<figure id="fig-punch-in-out-buttons"> 
  <title>The punch buttons set for a punch in and out</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/punch-in-out-buttons&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
You can use punch in and out separately if you wish; if, for example,
you have a definite punch-in point but are not sure how long the
recording should go on for, simply turn off punch out and Ardour will
keep recording.
</para>

</section> <!-- Punch in/out -->

<section><title>Step entry</title>

<para>
An alternative to recording MIDI with the transport rolling is
<emphasis>step entry</emphasis>.  This is a means of entering note
data without having to worry about getting your timing right.
</para>

<para>
To enter step-entry mode for a MIDI track, right-click its record
enable button and choose <guimenuitem>Step Entry</guimenuitem> from
the menu that pops up.  This will open the step entry dialogue, as
shown in <xref linkend="fig-step-entry"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-step-entry"> 
  <title>The MIDI step entry dialogue</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="diagrams/step-entry&dia;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Clicking one of the piano keyboard keys will put a note, of the
appropriate pitch, at the edit point.  The next note will be put after
the first one in time, and so on.  A step edit &lsquo;insert
position&rsquo; is displayed as a dark-red rectangle within the MIDI
track to indicate where the next note will go, and how long it will
be.
</para>

<para>
The buttons in the step entry dialogue change things about the note
that will be entered.  We have:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Chord entry</emphasis> &mdash; if this is selected and you
click on several notes one after the other, they will be placed at the
same time (as a chord) rather than one after the other.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Note duration</emphasis> &mdash; these buttons set the
duration of the note to be entered, using musical symbols.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Triplet</emphasis> &mdash; if this is selected, the selected
note duration becomes a triplet so that now three notes fit into the
time that two would previously have occupied.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Dotted</emphasis> &mdash; makes the note
one-and-a-half-times longer.  The double-dot makes it 1.75 times
longer, and the triple-dot 1.875.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Sustain</emphasis> &mdash; if you have selected notes, this
button extends them by the current note length.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Rest</emphasis> &mdash; inserts a rest (an empty space) of
the current note length.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>G-Rest</emphasis> &mdash; inserts a rest of for the length
of a grid space.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Back</emphasis> &mdash; move the step-edit insert position back by
the current note length.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>>Beat</emphasis> &mdash; move the step-edit insert position onwards by one beat.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>>Bar</emphasis> &mdash; move the step-edit insert position onwards by one bar.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>>EP</emphasis> &mdash; move the step-edit insert position to the edit point.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Velocity</emphasis> &mdash; set the velocity (volume) of the
notes that will be inserted, using musical terminology
(<emphasis>ppp</emphasis> being the quietest and
<emphasis>fff</emphasis> the loudest).
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Numerical entry</emphasis> &mdash; these entries allow the
setting of various parameters numerically.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Bank</emphasis> &mdash; this allows you to insert a bank
change; set the required bank number then click the
<guibutton>+</guibutton> button.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>Program</emphasis> &mdash; this allows you to insert a
program change; set the required program then click the
<guibutton>+</guibutton> button.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section> <!-- Step entry -->

</chapter>


