<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Sessions</title>

<para>
This chapter discusses Ardour sessions in more detail.
</para>

<section><title>Sessions, session files and snapshots</title>

<para>
Generally speaking when we talk about an Ardour &lsquo;session&rsquo;
we mean a directory that contains everything related to the session:
all Ardour's data and the sound files.
</para>

<para>
A session consists of two main things.  Firstly, we have the session
state file: this is Ardour's description of what happens in the
session.  It contains lists of tracks, regions, what sound files are
used, automation data, the connections between things, and so on.  It
does <emphasis>not</emphasis>, however, contain any audio or MIDI
data.  These data are kept separately, in their own files, using
standard formats.
</para>

<para>
The session state file is stored on disk with the suffix <code>.ardour</code>.
</para>

<para>
It is eminently possible that we might have more than one session
state file describing a different arrangement of the same sound files.
Perhaps there is a mix that was sent to a client, and a new mix that
you are working on, and you want to be able to refer back to the old
mix.  Alternatively, perhaps you are about to try something drastic
with a session, and it would make sense to keep an old copy of the
session just in case you change your mind.  Ardour can manage these
situations using <emphasis>snapshots</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
A snapshot is simply a session state file.  A particular session
directory may contain many snapshots, each looking at the same set of
audio and MIDI data and describing a different arrangement of the raw
data.
</para>

<section><title>Taking and switching between snapshots</title>

<para>
To make a snapshot of the current state of a session, simply choose
<guimenuitem>Snapshot&hellip;</guimenuitem> from the
<guimenu>Session</guimenu> menu or press
<keycombo><keycap>&modtertiary;</keycap><keycap>&modone;</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo>.
This will open a dialogue box for you to give the name of the new
snapshot; the name is initially filled in with the current date and
time.  Clicking <guibutton>Save</guibutton> will create the snapshot.
</para>

<para>
To look at the snapshots of the current session, open the editor list
and select the <guibutton>Snapshots</guibutton> tab.  The list will
show the existing snapshots, with a blue highlight on the current one.
Clicking on an alternate snapshot will switch to it.
</para>

<para>
You can rename or remove snapshots by right-clicking on their
names in the editor list and choosing an option from the menu.
</para>

<para>
Edits that you make to the session are always saved to the current snapshot.
</para>

</section> <!-- Taking and switching between snapshots -->

</section> <!-- Sessions, session files and snapshots -->

</chapter>
