<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Synchronisation</title>

<para>
Ardour provides various facilities for synchronising itself with other
programs or devices.  There are a couple of slightly different
approaches to doing this.  Firstly, we may want to synchronise our
transport speed with something else.  Secondly, it is often useful to
<emphasis>also</emphasis> synchronise time code, so that if the
&lsquo;playheads&rsquo; of all synchronised things are in the same
place.
</para>

<para>
Ardour can synchronise both transport speed and time code using one of two methods:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>MIDI time code (MTC)</emphasis> &mdash; this is a protocol which
communicates time code over MIDI; it is commonly used with
external devices such as tape or digital recorders.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>JACK transport</emphasis> &mdash; JACK provides support to
synchronise client applications, including Ardour.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If only speed synchronisation is required, there is the other option
of MIDI clock.  This is another MIDI protocol, but is much simpler
(and less capable) than MIDI time code.  It is often used by
synthesizers to synchronise the speed of delays, and so on.
</para>


<section><title>MIDI time code</title>

<para>
Ardour can both transmit and receive (chase) MIDI time code.  To
transmit it, tick the <guilabel>Send MIDI Time Code</guilabel> option
in the <guilabel>MIDI</guilabel> tab of <guilabel>Ardour
Preferences</guilabel>.  Ardour will then emit MTC from its &lsquo;MTC
out&rsquo; port.  Use the MIDI connection manager (see <xref
labelend="sec-manual-connections"/>) to connect this port to anything
that should chase Ardour's MTC.
</para>

<para>
Ardour will stop transmitting time code when the transport speed is a
certain percentage faster or slower than normal.  The amount either
side of normal speed to keep transmitting MTC is configurable in the
<guilabel>MIDI</guilabel> tab of <guilabel>Ardour
Preferences</guilabel>.
</para>

<para>In order to chase incoming MIDI time code, set the external time
code source to be &lsquo;MIDI Timecode&rsquo; in the
<guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> dialogue.  Note that if the positional sync
button in the editor window (see <xref labelend="ch-positional-sync-button"/> is already
set to something other than internal, you will need to set it back to
internal first.  Connect your MIDI time code source to Ardour's
&lsquo;MTC in&rsquo; port using the MIDI connection manager.  Then
click the positional sync button to enable chase.
</para>

</section> <!-- MIDI timecode -->


<section><title>JACK transport</title>

<para>
To enable synchronisation via JACK transport, set the external
timecode source to &lsquo;JACK&rsquo; in the
<guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> dialogue.  Note that if the positional sync
button in the editor window (see <xref
labelend="ch-positional-sync-button"/> is already set to something
other than internal, you will need to set it back to internal first.
Finally, click the positional sync button in the editor window (see
<xref labelend="ch-positional-sync-button"/>) so that is says
&lsquo;JACK&rsquo;.
</para>

<para>
If you want Ardour to be the JACK &lsquo;time master&rsquo;, that is
the program that dictates tempo and other information to the other
applications, tick the &lsquo;Ardour is JACK Time Master&rsquo; button
at the bottom of the <guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab in
<guilabel>Session Properties</guilabel>.
</para>

</section> <!-- JACK transport -->


<section><title>MIDI clock</title>

<para>
To set Ardour to transmit MIDI clock, tick the <guilabel>Send MIDI
Clock</guilabel> option in the <guilabel>MIDI</guilabel> tab of
<guilabel>Ardour Preferences</guilabel>.  Ardour will then emit MIDI clock
from its &lsquo;MIDI clock out&rsquo; port.  Use the MIDI connection manager
(see <xref labelend="sec-manual-connections"/>) to connect this port
to anything that should listen to Ardour's MIDI clock.
</para>

<para>In order to chase incoming MIDI clock, set the external time
code source to be &lsquo;MIDI Clock&rsquo; in the
<guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> dialogue.  Note that if the positional sync
button in the editor window (see <xref labelend="ch-positional-sync-button"/> is already
set to something other than internal, you will need to set it back to
internal first.  Connect your MIDI clock source to Ardour's
&lsquo;MIDI clock in&rsquo; port using the MIDI connection manager.  Then
click the positional sync button to enable synchronisation.
</para>

</section> <!-- MIDI clock -->

<section><title>Timecode options</title>

<para>
There are some other time code options in the
<guilabel>Timecode</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Session
Properties</guilabel> dialogue.
</para>

<section>
<title>Timecode frames-per-second</title>

<para>
This should be set to the frames-per-second count for the timecode
that you are syncing to, or that you want Ardour to generate.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Subframes per frame</title>

<para>
This should be set to the number of subframes per frame for the
timecode you are syncing to, or that you want Ardour to generate.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Timecode source shares sample clock with audio interface</title>

<para>
Enabling this option will make Ardour assume that the timecode is
exactly synchronised with the audio sample clock; in this case, the
two cannot drift apart.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Pull up/pull-down</title>

<para>
This should be set to the pull-up or pull-down for the
timecode you are syncing to, or that you want Ardour to generate.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Timecode offset (and timecode offset negative)</title>

<para>
These options should be set to reflect any required offset between
Ardour's session times and the timecode being received or
generated.
</para>

<para>
If the timecode is &lsquo;ahead&rsquo; of Ardour's timeline, the
offset should be positive; otherwise, set it negative.
</para>

</section>

</section> <!-- Other timecode options -->

</chapter>

