<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-tracks-and-busses" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Tracks and busses</title>

<para>
The basic building blocks of Ardour's sessions are <emphasis>tracks</emphasis>
and <emphasis>busses</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
Both are built on the same foundation; a bus' functionality is a
subset of a track's.  Both can pass audio and MIDI data, apply
processing and perform various signal routing operations.  The
difference with a track is that can record and play back data.
</para>

<section>
<title>Track and bus basics</title>

<section>
<title>Types</title>

<para>
An Ardour track can be either &lsquo;audio&rsquo; or &lsquo;MIDI&rsquo;.  The only real
difference between the two is the type of data that the track will
record and play back.  Either type of track can
<emphasis>pass</emphasis> either type of data.  Hence, for example,
one might have a MIDI track that contains an instrument plugin; such a
track would contain MIDI data, but would produce audio, since the
instrument would turn the one into the other.
</para>

<para>
In Ardour 3 busses are only used for audio.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adding and removing tracks</title>

<para>
A track or bus can be added to a session in various ways:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem> Choose <guimenuitem>Add Track or Bus&hellip;</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>Track</guimenu> menu.
</listitem><listitem> Right-click in an empty part of the track controls area.
</listitem><listitem> Click the + button underneath the list of tracks in the mixer.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Any of these actions will open the <emphasis>Add Track or Bus</emphasis> dialogue,
as shown in <xref linkend="fig-add-track-or-bus"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-add-track-or-bus"> 
  <title>Add Track or Bus dialogue</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/add-track-or-bus&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
From here, you can select firstly the number of tracks or busses to
add, and the type; audio track, MIDI track or bus.  There are also
some options, which vary depending on the type of thing you are
creating.
</para>

These options are:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem> Configuration (for audio tracks and busses) &mdash; this is the
  number of input and outputs the track is set up with.  You can
  always change these counts later.
</listitem>
<listitem>
Track mode (for audio tracks) &mdash; this can be &lsquo;normal&rsquo;,
&lsquo;non-layered&rsquo; or &lsquo;tape&rsquo;.
<!--  I have no idea what non-layered nor tape modes do -->
</listitem>
<listitem>
 Group &mdash; tracks and busses can be put into groups so that a
  selected range of operations are applied to all members of a group
  at the same time (selecting record enable, or editing, for example).
  This option allows you to specify an existing group to add the new
  track(s) or bus(ses) to, or to create a new group to put the new
  things in.
</listitem>
<listitem>
 Instrument (for MIDI tracks) &mdash; this is a short-cut to allow you
 to create a MIDI track with an instrument plugin already added to it.
 You can achieve the same effect by creating a MIDI track with no
 plugins and adding it yourself; this option just makes things
 slightly quicker.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Adding tracks will add them to both the editor and mixer windows; the
editor window shows the timeline, with any recorded data, and the
mixer shows just the processing elements of the track (its plugins,
fader and so on).
</para>

<para>
Tracks and busses can be removed by selecting them, right-clicking and
choosing &lsquo;Remove&rsquo; from the menu.  A warning dialogue will pop up, as
<emphasis>track removal cannot be undone</emphasis>; use this option with care!
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="sec-track-and-bus-groups">
<title>Track and bus groups</title>
<indexterm><primary>group</primary></indexterm>

<para>
Tracks and busses can be put into <emphasis>groups</emphasis>. The members of a
group can be set to share various settings, which can be useful for
managing tracks which are closely related to each other.  Examples
might include tracks that contain multiple-microphone recordings of a
single source (an acoustic guitar, perhaps, or a drum-kit).
</para>

<para>
You can put tracks and busses into groups in various ways.  In the
editor window, a track's controls might look like those in
<xref linkend="fig-track-in-group"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-track-in-group"> 
  <title>The header of a track in a group</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/track-in-group&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The green tab to the left of the track header indicates that this
track is in a group called &lsquo;Fred&rsquo;.  These tabs can be dragged in the
editor window to add to or remove tracks from groups.  Alternatively,
clicking the &lsquo;g&rsquo; button opens a menu which gives a list of the
available groups; selecting one of these groups will add the track or
bus to that group.  This menu also allows a new group to be created.
</para>

<para>
The properties of a group can be edited by right-clicking on its tab
and choosing <guimenuitem>Edit Group&hellip;</guimenuitem>.  This will
open the track/bus group dialogue, which is also used when creating
new groups, as shown in <xref
linkend="fig-route-group-dialogue"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-route-group-dialogue"> 
  <title>The track/bus group dialogue</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/route-group-dialogue&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
&lsquo;Active&rsquo; means that the group is being obeyed, so that the sharing of
properties is applied to its members.  The colour can be changed, and
affects the colour of the group's tab in the editor and mixer windows.
</para>

<para>
Following these options are a list of the things that the members of
the group can share.  &lsquo;Gain&rsquo; means that the track faders will be
synced to always have the same value; &lsquo;Relative&rsquo; means that the gain
changes are applied relative to each member's current value.  If, for
example, there are two tracks in a group with relative gain sharing,
and their faders are set to -3dB and -1dB, a change of the first
track to a gain of -6dB will result in the second track having a
gain of -4dB (so that the difference in gains is the same).
</para>

<para>
&lsquo;Muting&rsquo;, &lsquo;soloing&rsquo;, &lsquo;record enable&rsquo;, &lsquo;route active state&rsquo;, &lsquo;colour&rsquo;
and &lsquo;monitoring&rsquo; are all straightforward; they simply mean that all
member tracks or busses will share the same settings in these
respects.
</para>

<para>
&lsquo;Selection&rsquo; means that if a region is selected or deselected on one
constituent track, corresponding regions on other member tracks will
be similarly selected.  Corresponding regions are those that are at
the same position and have the same length.  Similarly, &lsquo;Editing&rsquo;
means that edits applied to one track will be applied at the same
place on other tracks in the group.  These options are particularly
useful for multi-microphone recordings, where you always want to apply
the same edits to each track.
</para>

<para>
Right-clicking on the group tab offers a further menu of group-related
actions.  <guimenuitem>Create a New Group</guimenuitem> does as its name suggests, and
there is also an option to create a new group and automatically put
particular tracks into it.  <emphasis>Collect Group</emphasis> moves all the member
tracks so that they are together in the editor window, and
<guimenuitem>Remove Group</guimenuitem> removes the group (and only the group, not its
members).
</para>

<para>
<guimenuitem>Add New Subgroup Bus</guimenuitem> creates a bus (giving
it the name of the group) and connects the output of each member to
the new bus.  In a similar way, <guimenuitem>Add New Aux
Bus</guimenuitem> adds a bus and gives each member a send to that bus.
There are two options for this, specifying whether the sends should be
placed pre- or post-fader.
</para>

<para>
Finally, <guimenuitem>Fit to Window</guimenuitem> will zoom the member
tracks so that they fill the editor window.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Tracks and busses in the editor window</title>

<para>
When a track or bus is added to a session it is given a representation
in both the editor and the mixer windows.  Broadly speaking, the
editor window shows the track's timeline, and the mixer window its
signal processing.
</para>

<para>
On the left of a track or bus in the editor is the controls area.  The
contents of this area are different for audio tracks, MIDI tracks and busses.
</para>

</section>
<section>
<title>Busses</title>

<para>
A typical control area for a bus is shown in <xref
linkend="fig-typical-bus-controls"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-typical-bus-controls"> 
  <title>Controls for a typical bus</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/typical-bus-controls&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
At the top-left of the controls is the name of the bus.  This can be
edited directly to whatever is suitable, although the name must be
unique within the session.  Underneath the name is a copy of the bus'
main level fader.  The control buttons to the right-hand side are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<emphasis>&lsquo;m&rsquo;</emphasis> &mdash; mute &mdash; left-click to mute the
bus.  Right-click to display a menu which dictates what particular
parts of the bus should be muted. <!-- detail of muting options -->
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>&lsquo;s&rsquo;</emphasis> &mdash; solo &mdash; solo the bus.  The
behaviour of the solo system is described in detail in <xref
linkend="sec-mute-and-solo"/>.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>&lsquo;a&rsquo;</emphasis> &mdash; automation &mdash; click to open a
menu related to automation for the bus.  Automation is covered in
<xref linkend="ch-automation"/>.
</listitem>
<listitem>
<emphasis>&lsquo;g&rsquo;</emphasis> &mdash; group &mdash; click to open a menu
related to the bus group, as discussed in <xref
linkend="sec-track-and-bus-groups"/> above.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>
<section><title>Audio tracks</title>

<para>
A typical control area for an audio track is shown in <xref linkend="fig-typical-audio-track-controls"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-typical-audio-track-controls"> 
  <title>Controls for a typical audio track</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="screenshots/typical-audio-track-controls&scs;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
An audio track has the same controls as a bus, with the addition of
two extras.  The red button with the pink circle is the track's
<emphasis>record enable</emphasis>.  When this is clicked it will gain a bright red
outline, and the track will then be recorded onto when the main
session record enable is turned on with the transport rolling.
</para>

<para>
The &lsquo;p&rsquo; button below the record enable will open a playlist menu when
clicked.  The menu offers various operations related to the track's
playlist.  This, as you will recall, is simply a list of the
regions that the track should play.  Playlists may be swapped on a
given track, and may be used by more than one track at the same time.
They are often useful to keep different takes, for example, or to
allow one set of regions to be played off two tracks with different
processing.
</para>

<!-- playlist menu details -->

</section>
<section><title>MIDI tracks</title>

<para>
A typical control area for a MIDI track is shown in <xref linkend="fig-typical-midi-track-controls"/>.
</para>

<figure id="fig-typical-midi-track-controls"> 
  <title>Typical MIDI track controls</title> 
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject> 
      <imagedata fileref="diagrams/typical-midi-track-controls&dia;"/>
    </imageobject> 
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The MIDI track example is shown at a greater height than the other
examples, as with MIDI tracks there are some control elements which
only appear when there is sufficient vertical space to fit them in.
</para>

<para>
A MIDI track has the same basic controls as an audio track, with the
addition of two extra elements.  The set of buttons below the main
track controls controls the MIDI channels that should be visible in
the editor.  A MIDI track's data may span any number of the 16
available MIDI channels, and sometimes it is useful to view only a
subset of those channels; different instruments may, for example, be
put on different MIDI channels.  Clicking on a channel number toggles
its visibility.
</para>

<!-- What does Force do -->

<para>
To the right of the MIDI track controls is a representation of a piano
keyboard called the &lsquo;scroomer&rsquo;.  This performs a couple of functions.
Firstly, the scroll-bar controls the range of pitches that are visible
on the track.  Dragging the scroll-bar body up and down scrolls up and
down through the visible pitches, and dragging the scroll-bar
&lsquo;handles&rsquo; zooms in and out, so that more or fewer pitches are visible.
The piano keyboard gives a reference for the pitches that the track is
displaying.  In addition, clicking on the notes will generate the
corresponding MIDI note in the track.
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

