<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN"
   "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
<!ENTITY % keys SYSTEM "keys.ent">
%keys;
<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "extensions.ent">
%extensions;
]>

<chapter xml:id="ch-troubleshooting" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<title>Troubleshooting</title>

<para>
Into each life a little rain must fall.  This chapter discusses what
to do if you are having problems with Ardour.
</para>

<section><title>Starting Ardour from the terminal</title>

<para> Much troubleshooting is made easier if you start Ardour from a
terminal such as &lsquo;GNOME Terminal&rsquo; or &lsquo;kterm&rsquo;.
Ardour prints useful messages to the terminal when it starts, and as
it runs, and they can give clues to your troubles.  Once you have
opened a terminal window you can often start Ardour with:
</para>

<programlisting>
ardour3
</programlisting>

<para>
If you are using a beta release of Ardour, try something like:
</para>

<programlisting>
/opt/Ardour-3.0beta3_11482-dbg/bin/ardour3
</programlisting>

<para>
replacing <code>Ardour-3.0beta3_11482-dbg</code> with the name of a
folder in <code>/opt</code>.
</para>

</section> <!-- Starting Ardour from the terminal -->

<section><title>Startup warnings</title>

<section><title>Your system has a limit for maximum amount of locked memory!</title>

<para>
This warning can range in importance from minor to major, but is worth
fixing anyway as it can cause very strange misbehaviours when you
least expect them.
</para>

<sidebar>
<para>
Modern operating systems use <emphasis>swap files</emphasis>, which
are areas of hard disk used like extra (very slow) RAM.  Swap files
can improve overall system performance greatly, as if there are areas
of memory that are not being accessed very much they can be kept
(temporarily) on disk, and the memory used instead for more helpful
things like caches.  The use of swap files means, however, that an
application may find that a simple access to its memory may lead to a
potentially long disk access that it was not expecting.  For many
applications this is not a problem, but for audio software is is
disastrous, as the delay in response may mean that time deadlines for
processing audio are missed.  To avoid this problem, Ardour tells the
operating system that it should not swap any of its memory to disk.
However, the ability to do this can be used for nefarious purposes by
ill-behaved applications, so it is usually limited by the operating
system.  This warning means that your machine has a limit for the
amount of locked memory.  If Ardour asks for more than that limit, the
operating system will refuse, potentially leading to problems.
Usually the most practical answer to this is to set your machine to
have a fairly large limit on locked memory (say, for example,
three-quarters of your total RAM).
</para>
</sidebar>

<para>
The fix for this warning is to edit a file which, on most Linux
distributions, is called <code>/etc/security/limits.conf</code>.  The
bottom of this file will usually look something like this:
</para>

<programlisting>
#&lt;domain>      &lt;type>  &lt;item>         &lt;value>
#

#*               soft    core            0
#root            hard    core            100000
#*               hard    rss             10000
#@student        hard    nproc           20
#@faculty        soft    nproc           20
#@faculty        hard    nproc           50
#ftp             hard    nproc           0
#ftp             -       chroot          /ftp
#@student        -       maxlogins       4
</programlisting>

<para>
To set up a limit for locked memory for members of the
<code>audio</code> group, add a line like this:
</para>

<programlisting>
@audio - memlock 4121440
</programlisting>

<para>
where the number at the end is the maximum amount of locked memory (in
kilobytes).  We suggest that you use three-quarters of the total, so
work out this number <inlineequation><alt>M</alt>M</inlineequation> using
</para>

<equation>
<alt>M = 786432 T</alt>
M = 786432 T
</equation>

<para>
where <inlineequation><alt>T</alt>T</inlineequation> is your total
memory in gigabytes.  So, for example for a machine with 2Gb of memory, add the line:
</para>

<programlisting>
@audio - memlock 1572864
</programlisting>

<para>
to the end of your <code>/etc/security/limits.conf</code>.  Finally, add your user to the audio group using
</para>

<programlisting>
sudo usermod -a -G audio fred
</programlisting>

<para>
where <code>fred</code> is your username.  Then log out and log in again so that the changes take effect.
</para>

</section> <!-- Your system has a limit for maximum amount of locked memory! -->

</section> <!-- Startup warnings -->

</chapter>
